g.23
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
Ukrainian American Citizens Club (Baltimore, Md.) Records
1923-1977
g.23
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
1.5 Linear feet 2 boxes, 3 bound volumes
The Ukrainian American Citizen's Club was one of the primary focal points of Ukrainian-American life in Baltimore, Maryland for many decades. The records in this collection document its founding as well as its activities from the 1930s to the 1950s.
Ukrainian American Citizen's Club (Baltimore, Md.).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Ukrainian American Citizen's Club and Ukrainian National Home of Baltimore, Maryland. It includes legal documents related to their incorporation, meeting minutes, correspondence, and other records, as well as records related to subsidiary organizations (such as the Ukrainian School). It also contains a limited number of records that predate the legal incorporation of the Club.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for researcher use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Biographical/Historical note
The Ukrainian American Citizen's Club and Ukrainian National Home were a central focus point for the Ukrainian American community in Baltimore, Maryland from the late 1920s to the 1970s. The Ukrainian American Citizen's Club began from an informal association in the 1920s, and was legally incorporated in 1931. The inital organizers included Peter Marmash, Theodore Nykula, George Ewanowicz, Andrew Peltz, Joseph Svobojohn, Joseph Prymak, Jacob Semenkow, John Rakochy, Michael Krist, and Alexander Ewachiw. Later officers and board members included (among others) George Pidhorniak (Podhorniak), John Malko, Milton Nykula, Joseph Fall, Omelian Dery, John Smolak, Nicholas Wozney, Joseph Semenkow, Vasile Stasiuk, and Joseph Marmash.
The Club purchased a property at 3101 O'Donnell Street, which became known as the Ukrainian National Home. It housed a school of Ukrainian language and culture, the Ukrainian American Citizen's Club Choir, the Vasile Avramenko School of Ukrainian Dancing, a Ukrainian American softball team, and provided space for a variety of community groups. In the post-World War II period, the National Home was used as barracks-style accomodations for displaced persons.
In 1969, the Club granted the Ukrainian Sports Club "Dnipro" the use of and responsibilities for maintainance of the Ukrainian National Home.
Custodial History
These records were in the possession of Club president Joseph Marmash and were inherited by his daughter Diana Marmash Carico, who donated them to the Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center.
Ukrainian Americans--Maryland--Baltimore
- Bylaws, deeds, and legal documents, 2 folders, 1 bound volume
  - Incorporation documents, bylaws, and legal matters, 1931-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1, Volume 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Original hand-written bylaws from 1931, as well as later typewritten and ammended bylaws, certificate of incorporation, articles of ammendment, articles of revival, tax exemption forms, and legal correspondence. It also includes transfer authorization and agreement related to the use of Club facilities by the Ukrainian Sport Club "Dnipro".
  - Deeds and mortgage documents, 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Record book, Bulk, 1931-1938; 1926-1938 (Volume 2)
  Contains member addresses, membership dues records, financial records (income, expenses, and proceeds from Christmas caroling), bylaws (of the Citizen's Club, the Ukrainian School, and the Ukrainian School Library), and meeting minutes. The back of the book also contains meeting minutes dated January 17, 1926 (prior to formal incorporation).
- Meeting minutes
  - General meeting minutes, 1948-1957 (Envelope 1, Volume 3)
  - Board meeting minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and other records, 5 folders
  - Correspondence, Bulk, 1953; 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership list (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee assignments, activities, and building improvements, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Income and expense ledger, 1932-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Blank stationery (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Phonograph recordings, 1.0 Linear feet (Box 2)
  78 RPM phonograph recordings that were played in the jukebox at the Ukrainian National Home.